Today’s דף Daf is ו. Vav. We pick up at the bottom
of עמוד ב. Amud Bet. Now, this is actually a central discussion
about the קרבנות Korbanot that we did not have at all in
פסחים, Pesachim, which is based on this פסוק Pasuk of ממשקה ישראל,
MiMashkei Yisrael, a פסוק Pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, from which we learn
out that קרבנות Korbanot have to be brought only from כשר Kosher
foods. And we are dealing with a ברייתא Braita that has a
possibility that maybe you would even bring it from a טריפה. Trefa.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara is saying that
it starts out how could you even think that you would bring
it from a
טריפה Trefa logically, make a קל וחומר Kal VaChomer that you wouldn't,
but if you had some argument, then we'll learn it out from
a פסוק. Pasuk. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say,
well, what argument could you have had? So let's take a look.
מאי אם השבת? Mai Im Hashavta? It is about 15 lines before
the lines get wide. It starts with the parentheses which says סימן
רקיע מר עד Siman Rakiach Mar Ad or whatever, so three words
before that. מאי אם השבת? Mai Im Hashavta? What could you have
responded that would have made you think that maybe a טריפה Trefa
would be כשר? Kosher? So here's what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
רב משום דאיכא למימר, Amar Rav mishum d’ika l’meimar, you could have
said, מנחת עומר תוכיח. Minchat Omer Tochiach. Don't say, don't make a
claim that something that's not כשר—now Kosher it didn't do it from
a פסוק, Pasuk, it just did it
logically—don't make a claim that something that's not כשר Kosher could not
be brought as a קרבן. Korban. How about the עומר? Omer? Every
year you bring the עומר Omer and at the moment you're bringing
it, it's still not כשר Kosher grain. It only becomes כשר Kosher
after it's brought, or at the moment it's brought, so it's a
little one of those sort of שתיים באחד. Shtayim B'echad. But how
about the מנחה Mincha of the עומר? Omer? תוכיח, Tochiach, that will
prove to you that this principle is not kept to, שאסור להדיוט,
she'asur l'hedyot, a normal person can't eat it yet, it's the new
grain, ומותר לגבוה, umutar l'gavoha, and it's permissible to be brought as
a קרבן Korban as a מנחה. Mincha. So the גמרא Gemara says,
nope, that would not have been a good argument because I could
have always said מה למנחת עומר שכן
מתרת? Ma leMinchat Omer sheken materet? That the מנחת עומר Minchat Omer
is different, that it is not forbidden, it actually makes itself permissible,
it makes other things permissible, it makes itself permissible, so that's not
a really good example of something not כשר Kosher that's brought as
a קרבן. Korban. So the גמרא Gemara says, שכן מתרת חדש. sheken
materet chadash. It makes the new grain permissible. So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, how about בשביעית? b'Shvi'it? How about on the שמיטה Shmita
year? So on the שמיטה Shmita year the grain is not permissible.
Now that's actually a funny question because of course you can eat
the food on שמיטה, Shmita, it has קדושת שביעית, Kedushat Shvi'it, but
you can eat it. So רש״י Rashi throws in here—actually he throws
in in the next line—that we're talking after the period of ביעור,
bi'ur, after the period that it's no longer available to the animals
in the field, that at that time... I think I might have
to answer this.
Excuse me just one second. Okay, so how about on שמיטה? Shmita?
Again, maybe we're assuming after the period of ביעור bi'ur where the
grain is not permitted, but that's a little bit
funny because as תוספות Tosafot asks that the period of ביעור, bi'ur,
isn't פסח Pesach around the time when the grain is just coming
out? How could you say that it's the time when it's no
longer available to the animals? So well, maybe it's the year after
שמיטה, Shmita, but then it's not permitting the grain because the grain
is always from the new year. So it's a little bit bizarre.
What does it mean that it does not make שביעית Shvi'it permissible?
Maybe not fully permissible because it's still restricted in how you have
to use it. It's a strange question. So the גמרא Gemara says,
שביעית נמי שכן מתרת ספיחים. Shvi'it nami sheken materet sevichim. Well, שביעית
Shvi'it will allow grain that was grown by itself. Okay? So it
won't allow the grain that was intentionally harvested. Now again, poor and
even you are allowed to harvest the grain on שמיטה, Shmita, you
just can't harvest it as if you are the owner. You can't
harvest it with that sense of ownership, however exactly that's defined. So
it's a funny idea—it's funny that it limits the issue to ספיחים.
sevichim. But it's saying at least stuff that grows by itself, it
allows. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, ספיחים בשביעית—no, sevichim b'Shvi'it so רבי עקיבא דאמר
ספיחים אסורין בשביעית. Rabbi Akiva d'amar sevichim asurin b'Shvi'it. What about רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says that even things that grow by themselves
are forbidden to be eaten? Now normally we assume that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is Rabbinic. You don't want to tell people 'oh, if
it grows by itself it's allowed' then everybody will say 'oh, these
bushels of wheat, they just grew by themselves, that's how come I
have all of them on שמיטה'. Shmita So therefore he wouldn't let
people eat things even if they grow on their own. But here
the גמרא Gemara seems to be assuming that it's biblical, דאורייתא, d'Oraita,
and therefore it says according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the עומר
Omer on שביעית Shvi'it does not—the grain still remains forbidden because it's
still שביעית Shvi'it produce and again, it's not really forbidden but okay,
anyway, it's not fully permissible. So therefore there's an example of a
קרבן Korban brought from a non-כשר Kosher product. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
where are we? אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב בר אבא
לרב אשי, Amar le Rav Acha b'rei d'Rab bar Abba l'Rav Ashi,
רבי עקיבא נמי ליפרוך. Rabbi Akiva nami lifroch. According to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that's not evidence that you bring a קרבן Korban from
something that's forbidden, מה למנחת עומר שכן מתרת חדש בחוץ לארץ. ma
l'Minchat Omer sheken materet chadash b'chutz l'aretz. At least it has the
effect that... not just simply something forbidden, it has the effect of
making חדש chadash permissible in חוץ לארץ. chutz la-aretz. Now again, we're
not denying that according to this argument we're saying that the מנחה
mincha itself is forbidden, but we're saying you can't prove from this
that in general you can bring a קרבן korban from something forbidden.
This might be a special exception because it has a power. What's
its power? It מתיר חדש matir chadash at least in חוץ לארץ
chutz la-aretz where שמיטה shmita doesn't apply. So and the גמרא Gemara
says ואפילו למאן דאמר חדש בחוץ לארץ לאו דאורייתא, Va-afilu le-man de-amar
chadash be-chutz la-aretz lav de-oraita, even if חדש chadash does not apply
in חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, major question for us, nevertheless it still
has a power, שכן בא להתיר לאו שבתוכה. sheken ba le-hatir lav
she-be-tokha. Even if it's not becoming totally permissible, laws of שביעית shvi'it
still apply to it, but nevertheless it is removing the prohibition of
חדש. chadash. It might not be getting it down to zero, but
at least when you bring it, it removes the prohibition of חדש
chadash and it makes itself more permissible, not fully. So you can't
prove to me from the עומר omer that we can bring a
קרבן—the korban general rule is we can bring a קרבן korban from
forbidden food. This might be a special exception because it has the
power to make it seems permissible. Are we done? I thought the
whole point was to try to prove about טרפה, treifa, right? Because
well, trying to say why did I need a פסוק pasuk by
טרפה? treifa? Why couldn't I have just made a קל וחומר kal
va-chomer to say you can't bring a קרבן korban from forbidden food?
So we had a whole ברייתא braita that said—proved you can't make
the קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. But even if you think you can,
I have a פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara is saying how
could I have thought you couldn't? So basically what we're now going
to deal with is trying to show what the הוה אמינא hava
amina of the ברייתא braita was, how maybe I could have made
an argument that you could bring a קרבן korban from non-kosher food.
And in a way, it serves as a nice demonstration that even
though we have this rule of מן המשקה ישראל, min ha-mashke yisrael,
there are a couple of exceptions. So that's why this—needs the פסוק
pasuk essentially? Yes, because you might have looked at those exceptions and
said you can bring a קרבן korban from non-kosher food, so therefore
you need a special פסוק pasuk from טרפה. treifa. Because you had
the whole חלב ודם chelev va-dam thing? Exactly. Okay. So that's what
we're doing. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar
lei Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina, אי הכי טרפה נמי תקרב ותתיר לאו
שבתוכה. ee hachi treifa nami tikarev ve-tatir lav she-be-tokha. Then even bring
the טרפה treifa and let it make its own prohibition permitted. Now
that's a crazy question and תוספות Tosafot doesn't understand it because what
does it make permitted? חדש—I Chadash mean the עומר omer makes חדש
chadash permitted. So רש"י Rashi says, well maybe I would have said
that's the חידוש, chidush, that the תורה Torah would allow me to
bring טרפה treifa and then it'll be מותר mutar to eat. But
why would I have said such a thing? I mean it's explicit
that the עומר omer permits חדש. chadash. So the question is like,
doesn't make sense, תוספות Tosafot doesn't understand it. Does it mean it's
just פגם המזבח? pegam ha-mizbe'ach? No. No. הלאו שבתוכה? Ha-lav she-be-tokha? No.
Okay. So anyway, so תוספות Tosafot doesn't understand it.
תוספות Tosafot says, look at the last two lines of the last
תוספות Tosafot שכן. she-ken. He says והלא אינו מתיר איסור שביעית, Ve-halo
eino matir issur shvi'it, so the עומר omer we just got through
saying doesn't מותר matir the שביעית shvi'it issue. So ולמה יתיר איסור
טרפה? Ve-lama yatir issur treifa? So why would a קרבן korban that's
a טרפה treifa get away with the prohibition of טרפה? treifa? So
תוספות Tosafot doesn't understand the question, neither do I. Okay. So I'm
not in better—I'm not better than תוספות Tosafot on this point. So
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, אלא פריך הכי, Ela parich hachi,
here's the reason that an עומר omer is not a relevant question.
מה למנחת עומר שכן מצותה בכך. Mah le-minchat omer she-ken mitzvata be-khach.
And that really is going to be the way we're going to
deal with all the exceptions. Are there a couple of exceptions of
קרבנות korbanot that come from non-kosher food? Yes, חלב, chelev, דם, dam,
the עומר. omer.
But all of those is exactly because the תורה Torah said yes,
that's how you bring the קרבן. korban. But it doesn't mean when
the תורה Torah specifically tells me this is the nature of the
קרבן, korban, it's the חדש, chadash, it's the חלב, chelev, then okay,
we allow for that exception, מצותה בכך. mitzvata be-khach. The תורה Torah
is telling you that's the nature of this קרבן. korban. But as
a general rule, if it doesn't tell me this is how you
bring it, I can't bring it from non-kosher food. Is that what
they're—is that what they were saying above in—by חלב ודם? chelev va-dam?
No, right before the two dots. דזמנין דמחשבו ליה אל מי שברור
לעבודה ודווקא ראוי לעבודה, De-zimnin de-machshvu lei el mi she-barur la-avoda ve-davka
ra'uy la-avoda, and they say לאפוקי מנחת עומר דלא חזיא דחידוש הוא.
le-apukei minchat omer de-lo chazya de-chidush hu. Yeah,
that's how תוספות Tosafot understood it. Okay. That's how תוספות Tosafot understood
it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, ריש לקיש אמר, Resh Lakish
amar, so we're back to our problem. How could I have thought
to make an argument that you could bring a טרפה? treifa? So
ריש לקיש אמר משום דאיכא למימר מפטם הקטורת יוכיח. Resh Lakish amar
mishum de-ika le-meimar mefatem ha-ktoret yokhiach.
How about the person that makes the, you know, incense, right? No,
well, we'll just see, the גמרא Gemara will re-qualify that. שאסור להדיוט,
She-assur le-hediot, a normal person—I'm not allowed to make קטורת ktoret for
a layperson's use, ומותר לגבוה, u-mutar le-gavo'ah, and I can make it
for God's use. So there's something that's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara
first of all says, מפטם גברא הוא. Mefatem gavra hu. The one
making it, he's a person. We're talking about the thing you're bringing.
What do you mean oh, the guy is allowed to? Right? We're
talking about can you bring a קרבן, korban, the object you're bringing,
can that be something forbidden? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא
פיטום הקטורת. Ela pitum ha-ktoret. Okay, so fine, so I mean the
thing that was made for the קטורת ktoret יוכיח. yokhiach. שאסור להדיוט,
She-assur le-hediot,
that type of a thing is forbidden to be used to be
done for a הדיוט, hediot, ומותר לגבוה, u-mutar le-gavo'ah, and it's מותר
mutar for God. Now again, it's not the same point. It's not
like the object, right? I mean, you know, the תורה Torah says
that It does say איש אשר יעשה כמוה ish asher ya'aseh chamoh
ואיש אשר יקח כמוה ve'ish asher yikach chamoh ואשר יעשה ממנה להריח
בה va'asher ya'aseh mimenah lehariach bah ונכרת מעמיו. venichrat me'amav.
So
you know that you're not allowed to to smell it so that
type of a thing is אסור asur for a normal person and
it is מותר mutar for God. What? All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says right well להריח. lehariach. So anyway the גמרא Gemara says
מה לפיטום קטורת mah le'pitum ketoret
no again that's not relevant שכן מצותה בכך. sheken mitzvatah bekach. Exactly.
Wait what was the whole question? I don't understand what the גמרא's
Gemara point is. It's sort of like the חלב chelev and דם
dam question. There are some things that the reason we're not allowed
to do it is because they're designated for God. So you can't
sort of ask the question of oh aren't you bringing a קרבן
korban from something that's forbidden? It's the opposite logic. The reason it's
forbidden is because God told us to do this for the קרבן.
korban. So it says you know oh the קטורת Ketoret that's forbidden
for you to you know to make this type of thing to
smell it and so on and you're bringing it to God. Well
it's forbidden to make it for a הדיוט hedyot but you were
never making it for a הדיוט. hedyot. No but that's the whole
argument is a טריפה treifah is אסור להדיוט asur l'hedyot right? And
the argument is you can never have anything אסור להדיוט asur l'hedyot
that's מותר mutar for God. Well what about the קטורת? Ketoret? And
the answer is well that's the whole מצוה. mitzvah. Okay fine. אמר
בריה דרבינא אמר משום פסיקא למימר שבת תוכיח. Amar brei de'Ravina amar
mishum pesika lemeimar Shabbat tochiach. Here's an evidence of something that's forbidden
for us and מותר mutar for God שבת. Shabbat. שכן אסור להדיוט.
sheken asur l'hedyot. Now we're no longer dealing with objects that are
being sacrificed that it's forbidden for a person to violate שבת Shabbat
a layperson שכן אסור להדיוט ומותר לגבוה. sheken asur l'hedyot u'mutar l'gavoha.
You can violate שבת Shabbat for God. So you see things that
are for... now it's sort of turning into like a larger type
of an almost מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah be'aveirah question. It's no
longer like the object is forbidden like food. It's things that you're
not allowed to do for yourself you shouldn't be allowed to do
for God. So how can we... we can't violate שבת Shabbat for
ourselves how could we violate it for God? You know in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Well what about... right... what about... maybe they're
going to talk about this... in ציצית tzitzis right? They say you
can make... oh very good okay. מה לשבת שכן הותרה מכללה אצל
הדיוט במילה. Mah le'Shabbat sheken hutra m'ichlalah etzel hedyot bemilah.
No שבת Shabbat sometimes we allow even for you not just for
God like if you need to do the מצוה mitzvah of מילה.
milah. So the גמרא Gemara says אטו מילה צורך הדיוט הוא? Atu
milah tzorech hedyot hu? What מילה milah is just for your lay
purposes? מילה מצוה היא. Milah mitzvah hi. It's for God it's to
do a מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore you're overall... you're not allowed to
violate שבת Shabbat for your own purposes but you're allowed to violate
it for certain you know religious purposes. מילה Milah goes for שבת.
Shabbat. Right now of course the funny thing is that it doesn't
suggest פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh right? And it would have sort of
also been interesting but it doesn't suggest it. Anyway the גמרא Gemara
says אלא... ela... but
that's not to God. What? But then... yeah but then why didn't
it raise that point?
Right because it rejected מילה milah as a counter-argument so why didn't
it raise פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? I mean you know
is the fact that it didn't raise פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh proves
that it's for you or does it also prove that it's for
God? Because they could have equally as rejected as מילה. milah. I
don't know it's hard to make arguments from silence. אלא מה לשבת
שכן מצותה בכך. Ela mah le'Shabbat sheken mitzvatah bekach.
Again that doesn't prove anything. The תורה Torah says you bring קרבנות
korbanos on שבת Shabbat you know certain קרבנות. korbanos. So again we're
not saying there can't be exceptions to a rule but the point
is what is the rule? So don't prove to me from you
know from קרבנות korbanos on שבת Shabbat or from קטורת Ketoret or
from חלב chelev and דם dam don't prove to me there's not
a rule that you can't bring קרבנות korbanos from things that are
forbidden or things that are forbidden to you you can't do for
God. That could be the rule unless the תורה Torah explicitly tells
us unless the תורה Torah explicitly tells us this is how you
have to do it. Okay so these exceptions don't prove that there
isn't a rule. Okay wait so you're saying because you can bring
things that are forbidden so therefore you should have been able to
bring a טריפה treifah which is why you need a פסוק pasuk
to... No but the point is you can't prove that the rule
is you're allowed to because all these things the תורה Torah explicitly
endorses them. So there's no proof that there's a rule that you're
allowed to bring some things that are forbidden. Okay let's take a
look.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara asks Michael's question. רב אדא בר
אהבה אמר משום דאיכא למימר כלאים תוכיח. Rav Adda bar Ahava amar
mishum de'ika lemeimar kilayim tochiach.
How about שעטנז? shatnez? שכן אסור להדיוט. sheken asur l'hedyot.
I'm not allowed to wear שעטנז. shatnez. ומותר לגבוה. u'mutar l'gavoha. But
you can have... what are the בגדים begadim of the כהן? Kohen?
It's the אבנט avnet right? Which has in it שעטנז. shatnez. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says... now again some some you know people
who do טעמי המצוות ta'amei hamitzvos say that that's exactly why it's
forbidden you know to the הדיוט hedyot it's because it's used by
the priestly garments so דווקא davka you shouldn't use תכלת techeiles either.
Well but...
well okay so then the question is right exactly where the lines
get drawn. All right anyway that's an interesting thing in general to
note the sort of paradoxes in the מקדש. Mikdash. Right you have
the כרובים keruvim you have the שעטנז shatnez you know you have
the types of things that you would normally not be doing for
yourself. All right anyway so the גמרא Gemara says... Is that allowed
to do that's what I mean. Right okay so the גמרא Gemara
says מה לכלאים שכן הותרו מכללן אצל הדיוט בציצית. Mah le'kilayim sheken
hutru m'ichlalan etzel hedyot be'tzitzis. No
those are not totally forbidden to a layperson you're allowed to wear
כלאים kilayim when? בציצית. Be'tzitzis. If you have wool... if you have
a linen garment you put on wool ציצית tzitzis because the תכלת
techeiles string has to be wool. Okay so the white strings can
be linen but the תכלת techeiles has to be wool. There's a
מצוה mitzvah of תכלת techeiles so even if you're wearing a linen
garment you can have שעטנז. shatnez. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute that's not allowing it for a layperson. אטו ציצית צורך הדיוט
היא? Atu tzitzis tzorech hedyot hi? מצוה! mitzvah!
That's not a lay person, that's for doing a מצוה. mitzvah. So
again, we've never proven that שעטנז shatnez is permissible for lay purposes.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא, ella, so now the top of
ו' עמוד א', vav amud aleph, מה לכלאים שכן מצוותו בכך נחם
לו. mah le-kilayim she-ken mitzvoso bekach nachum lo. The תורה Torah explicitly
tells us, right—it doesn't say explicitly, but you know, through the rabbis'
eyes it's explicitly, because it says לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו,
lo silbash shatnez tzemer u-fishtim yachdav, גדילים תעשה לך. gedilim ta'aseh lach.
So the juxtaposition tells us that if you need to, you can
have שעטנז shatnez in your ציצית tzitzis again, when you need because
the garment is linen and the תכלת techeiles has to be wool.
It's not מצוותו בכך mitzvosoh bekach to bring it from כלאים kilayim
though. I understand, but in this circumstance where you're wearing a linen
garment, you have no—no opportunity, no ability to do ציצית tzitzis without
doing כלאים. kilayim. Okay, as opposed to טריפה, treifa, nobody is obligating
me to bring a טריפה. treifa. Okay, so again you cannot prove
that when you have a choice, or the תורה Torah does not
explicitly allow it, that you're allowed to do these types of things.
So it'd be better to do the כלאים kilayim than the, say,
do the cotton, whatever it is, you know, threads or— Again, remember,
in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, ציצית tzitzis is not a
ritual garment that you wear to, you know, it's not the בגד.
beged. You happen to own a linen garment and then the תורה
Torah tells you, it's like you happen to own a house so
the תורה Torah tells you put a מזוזה mezuzah on it. So
you happen to own a linen garment, the תורה Torah tells you
you have to put ציצית tzitzis on it. So, right, now you
could say, well maybe I shouldn't buy a linen garment. All right,
but again, it's, you know, once you have that linen garment, you
have that מצוה. mitzvah. You never have a circumstance which has a
מצוה mitzvah to make you bring a קרבן korban of a טריפה.
treifa. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says, yes, are exceptions. So
again, what's interesting about this is in the course of trying to
say what would have the argument been that maybe a טריפה treifa
would be okay, it's giving the גמרא Gemara an opportunity to surface
all of the exceptions to the rule where we do מצוות mitzvos
with things which are otherwise forbidden. Now again, it's also broadening the
concept. It's not just a קרבן korban with forbidden food, it's מצוות
mitzvos with things which for lay people the action or the object
would have been forbidden. But it can't be—I would say הרי זו,
harei zu, it was a kosher קרבן korban at the time, then
it became טריפה. treifa. Ah, so the גמרא Gemara is actually going
to discuss that later on, but still, you know, that doesn't obligate
you to bring this. You could always redeem it if it's not
kosher. So, right, as opposed to if I want to wear this
linen garment, there's no way I can wear it without ציצית. tzitzis.
Okay, so רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר, Rav Sheshes brei de-Rav
Idi amar, top of ו' עמוד א', vav amud aleph, רב ששת,
Rav Sheshes, first line, רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר שיתא, Rav
Sheshes brei de-Rav Idi amar shita, whatever, אמר משום דאיכא למימר להדר
דינא ותיתי ממה הצד. amar mishum de-ika lemeimar lehadar dina ve-seisi mi-ma
ha-tzad. Okay,
you're right. There's no way we could prove just from any one
case that you can bring a קרבן korban from a non-kosher item,
but maybe we could prove it from a מה הצד, ma ha-tzad,
from a common denominator. What's the common denominator? So, מה למליקה, ma
le-melika, so we wanted to say before, look, you bring a קרבן
korban from מליקה melika where the bird is a נבילה, neveilah, you
שוחט shochet it from behind, right? So again, the answer was like
מצוותו בכך. mitzvosoh bekach. Okay, or קדושתו גרמה לו. kedushasoh garsah lo.
The גמרא Gemara says, מה למליקה, ma le-melika, so
how about מליקה, melika, doesn't that prove a קרבן korban from a
non-kosher thing? So you would say no, מליקה melika is different, שכן
קדושתו אסרתו, she-ken kedushasoh asartoh,
because of its קדושה, kedushah, that's why you did the מליקה melika
and that's a special case. So חלב ודם יוכיחו. chelev ve-dam yokichu.
So, okay, חלב ודם chelev ve-dam is something that you bring from
forbidden food. No, those have a distinguishing characteristic. What's their distinguishing characteristic?
מה לחלב ודם שכן באו מכלל היתר? mah le-chelev ve-dam she-ken ba'u
mi-kelal heter? The animal was kosher even though the חלב chelev and
דם dam was not. So מליקה תוכיח. melika sochiyach. מליקה melika will
prove that even though the animal, the entire animal is a נבילה,
neveilah, you would still bring it. וחזר הדין, ve-chazar ha-din, so you
go back and forth. What's distinctive about מליקה melika that that was
based on the קדושה kedushah is not true about חלב ודם. chelev
ve-dam. What's distinctive about חלב ודם chelev ve-dam that the rest of
the animal is kosher is not true about the מליקה. melika. וחזר
הדין, ve-chazar ha-din, לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי
זה. lo rei zeh ki-rei zeh ve-lo rei zeh ki-rei zeh. The
distinguishing characteristics of one is not like the distinguishing characteristics of the
other. הצד השוה שבהן, ha-tzad ha-shaveh she-ba-hen, the common denominator is, שאסורין
להדיוט, she-assurin le-hedyot, that both cases you have something that is forbidden
to a lay person, ומותרין לגבוה, u-mutarin le-gavoha, and nevertheless can be
brought as a קרבן. korban. אף אני אביא טריפה, af ani avi
treifa, אף על פי שאסורה להדיוט, af al pi she-asura le-hedyot, תהא
מותרת לגבוה. te-hei mutereset le-gavoha. So I'll say the same by a
טריפה, treifa, it's forbidden to a lay person, permitted as a קרבן.
korban. So they'd say, look, you brought me a lot of exceptions,
but I can say with all those exceptions, right, I will—I will
sort of eliminate the distinguishing characteristics because they're not the same across
the board. And the only rule that I can infer from all
those exceptions is that non-kosher animals can be brought as קרבנות. korbanos.
Because you'll say oh this exception is different for this reason, that's
different for that reason. Now it is true you could have ten
exceptions and each one has a special reason, but the גמרא's Gemara
logic is, is that no, you're—you know, if you don't have a
common reason then you can deny that any particular reason is the
cause. So the גמרא Gemara says that should have made an argument.
You could definitely be able to bring a חיה, chaya, I mean
I can—I can even eat it. Right, so that's—yeah, so that gets
raised and the answer is you know it's—it's not מן המובחר min
ha-muvchar or whatever but yeah okay. So then the גמרא Gemara says
like this, no, מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן מצוותן בכך. mah le-ha-tzad
ha-shaveh she-ba-hen she-ken mitzvosan bekach.
In all of these exceptions, the universal argument that there is different
is that the תורה Torah tells you basically that they are an
exception. Okay? So the תורה Torah is explicitly telling you this is
how you do it. Yes, you bring חלב chelev even though it's
אסור. assur. Yes, you wear כלאים kilayim in your ציצית. tzitzis. Yes,
you do מליקה. melika. So when the types of the common denominator
is the תורה Torah labels them as an exception and tells you
this is how you're supposed to do it. But that doesn't mean
when the תורה Torah doesn't tell you do it this way you're
allowed to, which is why we need a פסוק. pasuk. So that's
we're back to the question of why do we need a פסוק
pasuk to exclude טריפה. treifa. Again, in this process we're exploring the
question of what's the rule? Okay? So but it's not really giving
us any explanation for the deeper meaning here why these things are
אסור assur or מותר. muttar. Correct, correct. Oh, that is so not
the גמרא's Gemara's interest. The גמרא Gemara is only will only explore
that in the context of like אגדתא. aggadata. It does not explore
that in this type of a context. But clearly it was on
their minds because they've set up the entire
images around the angels with the wings. Right. But it's on their
minds not as like something religiously problematic. It's on their minds because
they just want to know what's the rule. Yes or no? You
know? Right, right. It's like a logical argument, just logic but not
necessarily right.
And I do think that once we go beyond the issue of
forbidden food, it is evoking the other סוגיא sugya of like מצוה
הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah, which is the larger point of, you
know, you don't do מצוות mitzvos through things that otherwise would be
forbidden actions or as a product of a forbidden action. But here
you do, right? שבת, Shabbos, exactly, right, exactly. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, so we still have the question of how could
I have thought to allow a טריפה? treifa? So אמר רב אשי
משום דאיכא למימר מעיקרא דדינא פירכא. Amar Rav Ashi mishum de'ika lemeimar
me'ikara de'dina pircha. Because I could have said that from the very
basis of the קל וחומר kal vachomer I would have had a
challenge. Why?
מהיכא קמייתת לה? Meheicha kamaisila? מבעל מום. Miba'al mum. The קל וחומר
kal vachomer was a בעל מום. ba'al mum. A בעל מום, ba'al
mum, a normal person can eat and you can't bring as a
קרבן. korban. Something that you can't eat, how much more so can
you not bring as a קרבן? korban? That was the basis of
the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So I could have challenged that. מה
לי בעל מום שכן אסור במקריב כקריב. Ma li ba'al mum sheken
assur bamakriv kikevev. A בעל מום ba'al mum is a bigger problem.
Why? Because not only is the קרבן korban פסול, passul, the מקריב,
makriv, the כהן kohen is פסול. passul. If a כהן kohen has
a מום, mum, he's also פסול. passul. So don't tell me, since
a בעל מום ba'al mum is פסול passul for a קרבן korban
and you can eat it, so something that's a טריפה treifa certainly
should be פסול. passul. Maybe the reason a בעל מום ba'al mum
it's פסול passul is because it has a larger scope, because it
even applies to a כהן. kohen. It's a worse problem. Okay, but
maybe just non-כשר kosher food would be acceptable. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה רב אחא סבא, Amlei Rav
Acha Sava, so רב אחא Rav Acha the elder said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, יוצא דופן יוכיח. yotzei dofen yochiach. How about a
Caesarean section? A baby born שלא עשה במקריב כקריב, shelo assa bamakriv
kikevev, a כהן kohen who's born through C-section is a כשר kosher
כהן. kohen. Only the animal is not כשר. kosher. ומותר להדיוט, Umuttar
lehedyot, I can eat such an animal. ואסור לגבוה, Ve'assur ligvoha, but
it can't be brought as a קרבן. korban. So you have something
that is a totally innocuous problem for me and it's a non-problem
for me, and it's a problem for a קרבן. korban. So certainly
something that's not כשר kosher for me should not be כשר kosher
as a קרבן. korban.
So the גמרא Gemara says, therefore you don't need the פסוק. pasuk.
So once again, you don't need the פסוק. pasuk. Okay,
ומותר להדיוט ואסור לגבוה. umuttar lehedyot ve'assur ligvoha. So no, I could
have challenged that back. I could have said that's not a good
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה לי יוצא דופן שכן אינו קדוש בבכורה.
Ma li yotzei dofen sheken eino kadosh bevichora. יוצא דופן Yotzei dofen
is a more weighty invalidity because if an animal is born first-born
and it's a יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, it's not a בכור bechor
because it says אשר יולד, asher yivaled, which חז״ל Chazal learn means
born naturally, born through a vaginal birth, not a C-section. Okay, so
therefore it says, look, a טריפה treifa at least is a בכור.
bechor. If a טריפה, treifa, if the first-born animal is a טריפה,
treifa, it still has קדושת בכור. kedushas bechor. And a טריפה treifa
does not have a larger invalidity. A כהן kohen who's a טריפה
treifa is still a כשר kosher כהן. kohen. So even though you'll
tell me, but look, things that are מותר muttar for you are
אסור assur for the מזבח, mizbei'ach, that's
because they're weightier for the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Either it makes a כהן
kohen forbidden or it's not a good בכור. bechor. But something that's
just a non-כשר kosher food like a טריפה treifa should maybe be
acceptable for the מזבח. mizbei'ach. That would have been the argument. Okay,
so let's take a look. But for יוצא דופן yotzei dofen you're
still a בכור, bechor, right? Just not for animal purposes. Yes, yes,
like for פי שנים pi shnayim you are.
Okay, so but you don't do פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. My sister
has thought that we would have so she has one sister is
married to a כהן, kohen, one sister is married to a לוי,
Levi, so they didn't have פדיון הבן pidyon haben for their kids.
So we finally thought we were for our first-born son, we were
going to have a baby boy, finally we were going to do
the first פדיון הבן pidyon haben in the family, and it was
a C-section.
So there you go. All right, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
יוצא דופן יוכיח. yotzei dofen yochiach. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara so
the
גמרא Gemara says בעל מום יוכיח. ba'al mum yochiach. Okay, so now
let's prove it from a בעל מום, ba'al mum, that that is
קדוש בבכורה. kadosh bevichora. No. But that has a different, that has
another reason why, why it's a more weighty problem. מה לבעל מום
שכן אותו מקריבים לקרבן? Mah l'baal mum sheken oto makrivim l'korban? It
also, the point is now we're doing the back and forth. We're
going to eliminate the special reasons and try to go to the
common denominator. יוצא דופן יוכיח. Yotzei dofen yochiach. Let's prove it from
יוצא דופן. yotzei dofen. That doesn't apply to כהנים. kohanim. וחוזר הדין.
V'chozer hadin. It goes back and forth. לא ראי זה כראי זה
ולא ראי זה כראי זה. Lo re'i zeh k're'i zeh v'lo re'i
zeh k're'i zeh. The distinguishing characteristics are not the same. הצד השווה
שבהם. Hatzad hashaveh shebahem. The common side denominator,
שמותרים להדיוט ואסורים לגבוה. shemutarin l'hedyot v'asurim l'gavoah. Here are things that
are permissible for a lay person and they're forbidden for the מקדש.
Mikdash. וכל שכן V'chol sheken or אף אני אביא af ani avi
טריפה treifah שאסורה להדיוט תהיה אסורה לגבוה. she'asurah l'hedyot tihyeh asurah l'gavoah.
So we still have our logical argument that טריפה treifah should be
forbidden. Things that are permitted for me are forbidden for God. Oh,
you'll say, well, they have other special problems. No, because all those
problems are unique in each category and you eliminate them, they're not
common. So the basic rule is even things that are permitted for
me are forbidden for God, certainly non-kosher things are forbidden for God.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. מה להצד השווה שבהם
שכן לא הותרו מכללן? Mah l'hatzad hashaveh shebahem sheken lo hutru michlalan?
But one minute, when it comes to בעל מום baal mum or
יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, we never make exceptions. They can never be
a good
קרבן. korban. אבל תאמר בטריפה שהותרה מכללה? Aval tomar b'treifah shehutrah michlalah?
But a טריפה treifah we do make exceptions. Now that's news to
me. When do we ever make an exception for a טריפה, treifah,
right? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי: Amar lei Rav Acha breih d'Rava
l'Rav Ashi: טריפה שהותרה מכללה מאי היא? Treifah shehutrah michlalah mai hi?
What's this case that you're saying that a טריפה treifah sometimes we
permit? אילימא מליקה דעולת העוף? Ileima melikah d'olat haof? So now here's
an interesting thing about the bird עולה. olah. Before it becomes a
נבלה, neveilah, it becomes a טריפה. treifah. Okay,
normally if I go ahead and I kill an animal incorrectly, so
at that moment it becomes a נבלה. neveilah. It doesn't happen in
stages. But what happens with the bird is if you're going from
behind, first you break the spinal cord, and that makes it a
טריפה treifah before you actually get to the esophagus or the trachea,
which is actually killing it. So you first have made it a
טריפה treifah before you killed it. And nevertheless, we're, you can eat
this. So even if
you, no, you don't. The כהנים. kohanim. So you see a טריפה
treifah becomes permissible. Just give me one second, Josh.
I have some instructions to pass on about this breakfast, which is
actually 8:00 now. Are you going to go?
So there's the master keys to the
שול shul are, all right. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, where are we? מאי היא אילימא מליקה דעולת העוף? Mai hi
ileima melikah d'olat haof? הא תינח מליקה Ha tinach melikah for a
bird עולה olah לגבוה, l'gavoah,
and that you give to God. So you see that even for
the מקדש Mikdash we allow something that's a טריפה, treifah, right? So
the גמרא Gemara says, בעל מום נמי בעוף ישתרי ישתרי. Baal mum
nami b'of yishtarei yishtarei.
You can't bring any proof from that because when it comes to
birds, we're more lenient in general with what type of קרבנות korbanot
are acceptable. You can even bring a bird that has a מום.
mum. So don't bring to me a proof from ways in which
birds were more lenient that I should be allowed to bring a
טריפה treifah animal. Birds in general were more lenient for קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay, בעל מום נמי בעוף ישתרי ישתרי Baal mum nami b'of yishtarei
yishtarei
because we say תמות וזכרות בבהמה. tamut v'zachrut b'behemah. The Torah says
that only the big animals, the mammals, have to be unblemished and
male for an עולה. olah. ואין תמות וזכרות בעוף. V'ein tamut v'zachrut
b'of. But for birds that are עולות olot or in general birds,
it does not have to be unblemished and does not have to
be male. אלא מליקה דחטאת העוף לכהנים. Ella melikah d'chatas haof l'kohanim.
This is what I was saying before. The כהנים kohanim can eat
the חטאת העוף. chatas haof. What were they saying right before this
then? That's the עולת העוף. olat haof. Don't proof to me, oh,
we go lenient on an עולת העוף, olat haof, we let it
be a טריפה treifah and we bring it as a קרבן, korban,
I should bring an animal קרבן korban as a טריפה. treifah. No,
we're generally lenient by birds in terms of קרבנות. korbanot. Oh, but
there's another leniency by טריפה. treifah. We even let the כהנים kohanim
eat it. So if sometimes we permit the prohibition of טריפה treifah
to a normal person, that maybe could be why we should allow
it an animal to be a טריפה. treifah. So maybe I'll concede
to you the general rule is non-kosher food no, but this type
of non-kosher food which sometimes is allowed, right, maybe special circumstances, but
allowed, maybe that will allow to bring as a קרבן. korban. All
right,
so the גמרא Gemara says כהנים משולחן גבוה קא
זכו. Kohanim mishulchan gavoah ka zachu. כהנים Kohanim are meriting by eating
off of God's table. Which means that they're not eating as laypeople,
they're eating as part of the consumption of the מקדש. Mikdash. And
therefore you cannot say, so it's similar to the general rule. The
same way by birds we go more leniently for them as קרבנות
korbanot מקדש. Mikdash. So when the כהנים kohanim eat them and they're
sort of eating them as part of the eating of the מקדש,
Mikdash, then it's part of the rule that we go lenient for
birds as קרבנות korbanot when they're being brought. But that's no proof
for an animal and we never go
lenient. No, you
just can't in animal it's
a problem. You can't take any special case by bird and go
outside of the category of bird. Birds are an exception. All right,
so the גמרא Gemara says, so we still have our question, right?
Why could I, how would I ever have argued that a טרפה
treifa should be good? I have no way as yet of arguing
that. So the גמרא Gemara finally says, אלא פרכא הכי, Ela parcha
hachi, here's the question: מה לצד השוה שבהן שכן מומן ניכר. Mah
letzad hashaveh shebahen sheken muman nikar. The two cases that you proved
are forbidden to God but permissible to me, which was יוצא דופן
yotzei dofen and a בעל מום, baal mum, at least their problems
are evident. Now what do you mean that a יוצא דופן yotzei
dofen its problem is evident like a בעל מום? baal mum? So
תוספות Tosafot says at the, it was, you know, especially at that
time. No, but it's in the person, in the animal,
right? So תוספות, Tosafot, you know, at that time presumably it was
so rare that it was well known and everybody said, oh, that
animal was born through a Caesarean section. That's what I'm saying. So,
oh, okay, fine. It's Caesar. What? Like Caesar and Shakespeare. Yeah, right,
it was very well known. But here it's, but it's also well
known about the animal. Okay, so there it's actually, but this is
fascinating about what ניכר nikar means. You know ניכר nikar does not
mean there's something physically discernible, ניכר nikar means it's all, you know,
ניכר nikar is through the eyes of the beholder. So if everybody
looks at this totally innocent animal and says, oh, בעל מום, baal
mum, not בעל מום, baal mum, oh, יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, that's
ניכר. nikar. So let me finish the sentence and maybe you'll understand.
Okay, so a מום mum and a יוצא דופן yotzei dofen is
מומן ניכר, muman nikar, and that's why it's אסור assur for the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. But תאמר בטרפה שכן אין מומן ניכר, Tomar betreifa sheken
ein muman nikar, but a טרפה treifa which is an internal injury,
nobody knows. And תוספות Tosafot makes it maybe even a little sharper
about, you know, טרפה, treifa, nobody in the world knows until it's
slaughtered, right? A יוצא דופן yotzei dofen at least there's some knowledge
of it even if it's not obvious. So maybe a טרפה treifa
where the whole problem is completely inaccessible and unknown to everybody, maybe
that should be a good קרבן. korban. So yes, it's not כשר
kosher to you, but everything, but maybe nevertheless what matters more in
the מזבח mizbe'ach is not כשר kosher versus non-כשר, kosher, but maybe
ניכר. nikar. And you know what? There's some truth to that, right?
Think about why we care about מום. mum. You know, there's in
the מקדש mikdash context aesthetics matter. So you know, and sort so
the symbolism and the aesthetics matter. So maybe if it's not כשר
kosher but nobody knows about it, it's not a big deal. Maybe
what matters more is what's externally noticeable. That's obviously a little bit
religiously difficult, right? What matters most in the מקדש mikdash is what's
on the outside, not on the inside. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara
says at least I could have had a הוה אמינא hava amina
that if it's not כשר kosher but it's unknown and unknowable, that
maybe that should, and then after you slaughter it you discover a
טרפה, treifa, maybe that should be okay. Wait, but then why do
we need
a... that's why we needed a פסוק. pasuk. No,
no, no, the גמרא Gemara says we have like a נבלה neveila
and a מוקצה muktzah and all that, right? Don't we have specific
פסוקים pesukim for that? Yes, and that's אסור assur for you. It's
אסור assur for you, what, because again what תוספות Tosafot would say,
no, no, those aren't אסור assur for you and it's not for
me, if it was only let's say נבלה neveila על ידי עד
אחד al yedei ed echad or something. There are, I mean מוקצה,
muktzah, you know, or נעבד ונסקל. ne'evad venisakal. No, מוקצה muktzah is
not אסור להדיוט. assur lehedyot. נעבד ונסקל על ידי עד אחד. ne'evad
venisakal al yedei ed echad. No, מוקצה muktzah is not... so the
פסוק pasuk is not coming to teach you like something that was
נבלה neveila and everybody and two עדים edim and all that, the
פסוק pasuk is coming to להוציא lehotzi even if it's נבלה neveila
על ידי עד אחד, al yedei ed echad, I still can't bring
it
to the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
That's what we need after we know the principle of ממשקה ישראל.
mimishkeh Yisrael. We have, okay, that's correct, but we haven't yet gotten
to that principle, because that's what's going to ask, why do you
need טרפה, treifa, you should also learn from that. So where are
we now? We're saying why do I need a פסוק pasuk by
טרפה? treifa? Because even though things that are less worse than טרפה
treifa are forbidden on a מזבח, mizbe'ach, they all are known. And
maybe if טרפה, treifa, the problem is completely unknown until after you
bring it, maybe that should be כשר. kosher. So therefore you need
a special פסוק. pasuk. So that already is a, you know, it's
a very good argument. תאמר בטרפה שכן אין מומן ניכר, Tomar betreifa
sheken ein muman nikar, by a טרפה treifa its blemish is not
known.
משום הכי איצטריך קרא. mishum hachi itztarich kra. Finally, we explained the
ברייתא braita why you need a פסוק. pasuk. Now we get to
the point why we brought this whole thing in. Why do you
need a פסוק, pasuk, what about the other general rule from ממשקה
ישראל? mimishkeh Yisrael? Meaning this was trying to prove it should be
not good based on like a קל וחומר kal vachomer inferring from
other cases, but don't we know from the
פסוק ממשקה ישראל pasuk mimishkeh Yisrael that anything that's not כשר kosher
is not a good קרבן? korban? So the גמרא Gemara says,
משום הכי איצטריך קרא. mishum hachi itztarich kra. טרפה מהכא נפקא, Treifa
mehacha nafka, is this where we learn it from, from this פסוק
pasuk of מן הבהמה? min habeheimah? מהתם נפקא, Mehatam nafka, we learn
it from this פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. And of course Michael
is correct, since when do we learn anything from a פסוק pasuk
in נביאים, Nevi'im, let alone say we don't need a פסוק pasuk
in the תורה? Torah? But the גמרא Gemara assumes, like it often
does from these things, obviously we must have had a מסורה. masorah.
And the פסוק pasuk is just a גילוי מלתא, giluy milta, but
anyway, the גמרא Gemara whenever it wants to say that something not
kosher is not good, it never bothers with this whole קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. It just says ממשובחת. mimshubachat. And תוספות Tosafot just says,
you know, that is the easy פסוק pasuk to latch on to,
to refer to this whole argument of why non-kosher things are not
good קרבנות. korbanot. So don't we learn it out from ממשקה ישראל,
mimashke Yisrael, מן המותר לישראל? min hamutar l'Yisrael? So and we have
another פסוק pasuk מכל אשר יעבור תחת השבט mikol asher ya'avor tachat
hashevet נפקא, nafka, פרט לטרפה. prat l'treifa.
We say that a מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema is anything that walks
under the stick as you're counting your animals: one, two, three, and
when you get to ten, that's מעשר. ma'aser. And it says that
a טרפה treifa is not considered something that walks under the stick.
Why not? Because sometimes טרפות treifot are sickly and they'll die early
and so on, so they don't, the image of health that you
get by walking under the stick is not appropriate by a טרפה.
treifa. So we learn from that פסוק pasuk that a טרפה treifa
isn't good for מעשר, ma'aser, and then we apply it to all
קרבנות. korbanot. We learn ממשקה ישראל mimashke Yisrael that it has to
be kosher. Who needs this special פסוק? pasuk? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says פרט לטרפה שאינה עוברת, prat l'treifa she'eina overet, excluding a
טרפה treifa that does not pass under. צריכי, tzerichi, you need all
three פסוקים. pesukim. דאי ממשקה ישראל, d'ei mimashke Yisrael, had it just
been from that פסוק, pasuk, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have
said למעוטי היכא דלא הויא לה שעת הכושר, l'ma'utei heicha d'lo havya
lah sha'at hakosher, that's only something that was never kosher. דומיא דערלה,
dumya d'orla, like bringing a מנחה mincha out of ערלה, orla, something
that was never kosher, right? Because from the very moment the fruit
formed, it was forbidden. וכלאי הכרם, v'kilay hakerem, or כלאיים. kilayim. אבל
היתה לה שעת הכושר, aval hayta lah sha'at hakosher, but something that
was initially permissible... right, so we're... good, I told you you anticipate
the גמרא. Gemara. So something like an animal that was born without
the טרפה treifa and got the טרפה treifa later, maybe that's not
as much of the identity of the animal, and if you know,
because it's not from the moment of birth, and if it's more
like the Greeks would call an accidental, you know, attribute and not
an essential attribute, so maybe therefore it's not so bad. אבל היתה
לה שעת הכושר, aval hayta lah sha'at hakosher, אימא תתכשר, eima titkasher,
maybe that will be accepted. So כתב רחמנא katav rachmana כל אשר
יעבור, kol asher ya'avor,
that's why it said the פסוק pasuk by מעשר ma'aser to tell
me, the extra פסוק pasuk adds even if it came later. ואי
כתב רחמנא v'ei katav rachmana כל אשר יעבור, kol asher ya'avor, had
it just had that, הוה אמינא hava amina למיעוטי היכא דנטרפה ולבסוף
הקדישה. l'ma'utei heicha d'nitreifa u'levasof hikdishah.
There you go Michael, that would have been maybe only a case
where the קדושה kedusha came after it became a טרפה, treifa, so
from the very outset it didn't have קדושה kedusha or appropriate קדושה.
kedusha. דבעידנא דאקדשה, d'be'idna d'akdeshah, אבל הקדישה ולבסוף נטרפה, aval hikdishah u'levasof
nitreifa,
first you sanctified it and then it became a טרפה. treifa. דבעידנא
דאקדשה חזיא הוה, d'be'idna d'akdeshah chazya hava,
at the moment you sanctified it it was fit, so maybe then
the fact that it became a טרפה treifa later would not undermine
its status. אימא תתכשר, eima titkasher, maybe it would be kosher. So
כתב רחמנא katav rachmana מן הבקר, min habakar, that's why you needed
the third פסוק. pasuk. צריכי, tzerichi, and therefore you need all three.
So at the end of the day though we say that anything
that is non-kosher food is not a kosher קרבן, korban, doesn't matter
whether it started its life that way, doesn't matter if it happened
later, if it happened after the קדושה. kedusha. So from these three
פסוקים pesukim we learn the general rule that whenever something gets to
the מזבח mizbe'ach and it's not kosher food, it's not a kosher
קרבן. korban. And as תוספות Tosafot says, the way we sort of,
you know, refer to all this whole argument is we just say
ממשקה ישראל mimashke Yisrael because that's a good, like, catchphrase to tell
us all these things. What was the פסוק pasuk again ממשקה ישראל?
mimashke Yisrael? How did it go? I forgot, you'll have to check.
Okay, so. And wasn't it something like it was really so obvious?
No. Okay. Really know better than to play like... But it's two
words! What are we supposed to say, מן הבהמה? min habehema? At
least ממשקה ישראל mimashke Yisrael makes you think to bring some juice,
something that is kosher. Okay. So now we go on ברוך השם
Baruch Hashem to the next משנה. mishna. And the next משנה mishna
gets us back to the... people, this will be, you know, a
parallel to a similar משנה mishna in זבחים Zevachim about what happens...
but this is much tighter than זבחים Zevachim in the sense that
זבחים Zevachim we started with שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, we had a
lot, a lot, a lot of שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, and then
we talked about other פסולים. psulim. Here we jump right in the
beginning to other פסולים. psulim. So the first פסול psul was שלא
לשמה. shelo lishma. Now we're going to talk about what if the
עבודה avoda was done with the wrong person. Okay, the... and we'll
see different types of wrong people. So let's take a look. אחד
מנחת חוטא ואחד כל המנחות, echad minchat chotei v'echad kol haminachot, whether
it's a מנחה mincha for sin or all מנחות, minachot, meaning normally
by
אינו לשמה, eino lishma, the מנחה mincha will still be כשרה keshera
even if the owners won't fulfill their obligation, but for the following
things, it's true about all מנחות. minachot. שקמצן זר, shekamtzan zar, if
a non-כהן kohen did the קמיצה. kmitza. אונן. onen.
Now by the way, remember, what's the הלכה halacha about שחיטה shchita.
*shchita*? Who can do the שחיטה? shchita. A זר zar can do
the שחיטה. shchita. But a זר zar cannot do the קמיצה, kmitza,
which is parallel to the שחיטה. shchita, Also a זר zar cannot
do the מליקה, mleika, right? We have special פסוקים pesukim to tell
you that a זר zar can't do מליקה, mleika, זר zar can't
do קמיצה, kmitza, but a זר zar can do שחיטה. shechitah A
זר zar can do all these other things, like בלילה, blila, יציקה,
yetzika, right? They take them later. No. That comes later. No, I
mean, can do like the... prior. Yes, but the קמיצה kmitza non-כהן,
kohen, the קמיצה kmitza which is parallel to שחיטה, shechitah which is
כשר בזר, kasher b'zar, is not כשר בזר. kasher b'zar. So I
think there could be two reasons why. One could be... Because since
these things are done with the actual hands of the כהן kohen
himself, the מליקה melikah and the קמיצה, kmitzah, so those hands are
actually functioning like a כלי שרת. kli shares. Okay? So therefore you
did you don't have a כלי, kli, you just have hands, so
the idea of you know of the hands as a כלי שרת
kli shares is a concept you can say by כהנים kohanim not
by non-כהנים, kohanim, whereas by שחיטה shechitah you do it with a
knife and at least according to some ראשונים rishonim the knife has
to be a כלי שרת. kli shares. So that's one approach. The
other approach is what תוספות Tosfos says about why שחיטה shechitah כשר
בזר kasher b'zar because the גמרא Gemara says and we're going to
see in a minute because שחיטה לאו עבודה היא, shechitah lav avodah
hi, which sort of begs the question. So one of the explanations
תוספות Tosfos has for שחיטה לאו עבודה shechitah lav avodah is because
you have to do שחיטה for lay purposes also, it's not a
specific מקדש Mikdash ritual. So that as opposed to קמיצה kmitzah and
מליקה melikah which are specific מקדש Mikdash rituals. So it's worth noting
that קמיצה kmitzah is not good with a זר zar but שחיטה
is. Okay, so let's take a look. שקמץ זר, shekamatz zar, a
non-כהן kohen did the קמיצה, kmitzah, אונן, onen, the כהן kohen was
an אונן, onen, a dead person died, a dead person, a relative
died that day. טבול יום, tvul yom, he was טמא tamei even
if he's gone to the מקוה mikvah and will be totally טהור
tahor that night, he's not a hundred percent טהור. tahor. מחוסר
בגדים, mechusar begadim, he's not wearing all or the right בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehuna. מחוסר כפורים, mechusar kippurim, he
basically the only thing that's between him and being a hundred percent
טהור tahor is bringing a קרבן. korban. Okay, like he was a
זב zav and it was after the whole process and the only
thing he has left is bringing a קרבן, korban, nevertheless he's not
a hundred percent טהור. tahor. So מחוסר בגדים mechusar begadim is more
like the טבול יום. tvul yom. שלא רחץ ידיו ורגליו, shelo rachatz
yadav v'raglav, he did not do רחיצת ידים ורגלים, rechitzas yadayim v'raglayim,
which a כהן kohen has to do. ערל, arel, if he is
uncircumcised even if he has no choice like it's a family of
hemophiliacs. טמא, tamei, if he's impure which of course because since we
also mention the lesser טומאות. tumahs. יושב, yoshev, if he's sitting because
it says לעמוד לשרת, la'amod l'shareis, that the עבודה avodah has to
be standing. עומד על גבי כלים על גבי בהמה, omed al gabei
kelim al gabei behemah, if he's standing on top of some vessel
or on top of the foot of an animal, על גבי רגלי
חבירו, al gabei raglei chaveiro, or on top of his fellow כהן's
kohen foot. Hey buddy, you're standing on my foot, is not just
telling me you're annoying me but also that your עבודה avodah is
פסולה. psulah. So in all those cases פסול. pasul. Why? Because his
feet have to, he doesn't even wear shoes or socks, his feet
have to directly touch the floor of the מקדש. Mikdash. It's all
bloody, I know, so yeah, we keep on raising that anyway because
to connect to the קדושה kedushah of the מקדש Mikdash and therefore
in any of these cases where there's something between his foot and
the מקדש, Mikdash, it's not acceptable.
Okay, קמץ בשמאל פסול. kamatz b'smol pasul. Let's say he used his
left hand, that is invalid as well. בן בתירא אומר, Ben Beteira
omer, בן בתירא Ben Beteira says, יחזיר ויחזור ויקמוץ בימין. yachzir v'yachzor
v'yikmotz b'yamin.
יחזיר, yachzir, put it back into the קמיצה kmitzah he took back
into the כלי, kli, יחזור yachzor do it again, ויקמוץ בימין v'yikmotz
b'yamin and now use your right hand. Now simple sense is you
can't do that, you cannot do that. So the simple sense of
this משנה Mishnah is that they are only arguing about the left
hand issue. For two reasons. Number one, it's not given in this
whole list. It's stated as an independent statement, right? After it says
פסול pasul about the long list, then it says קמץ בשמאל פסול.
kamatz b'smol pasul. So number one, it sounds like it's totally independent.
Number two is he says יחזור בימין. yachzor b'yamin. He doesn't say
יחזור yachzor and you should do it for כשר. kasher. So it
sounds like he has a specific point and this is an interesting
sort of conceptual point that the Briskers make a lot. The difference
between saying it's פסול pasul and saying it's not כשר. kasher. Because
there's this gap, right? Between being labeled as bad and just labeled
as not good, there's like this neutral space. So that בן בתירא
Ben Beteira could say all those things you mentioned, טמא, tamei, etc.
etc. etc. is פסול. pasul. Once it's labeled as a פסול עבודה,
pasul avodah, throw it out. But left hand is not like an
עבודה avodah at all. It's not maybe it's not a good עבודה
avodah but it's not פסול, pasul, maybe it's like a non-עבודה. avodah.
You know, maybe it's like I spilled a little or something like
that. So that you can reverse and go back. That seems to
be his position that he's distinguishing left from these cases which are
more deeper problems and maybe more we would label it as פסול.
pasul. The גמרא Gemara however is going to think that בן בתירא
Ben Beteira argues on the whole list. Okay. Why wouldn't there be
so much difference קמיצה kmitzah with your left hand versus like I
happened to be standing on your foot? Right, I could also just
go back and stand on the ground. Right, exactly, and you know
some of that so it's right. Both cases are as easily reversible.
So sometimes the question of do I label it as פסול pasul
or just not כשר, kasher, you know you could also go two
ways. Sometimes something could be not a problem because it is so
much out of you know so much like irrelevant sort of like
the מחשבה machshavah that was irrelevant that it's not a פסול עבודה,
pasul avodah, it's a non-עבודה, avodah, right? So something could be so
bad that it's not even an עבודה avodah at all, or something
could be more what you would sort of say like as a
technical as a so minor a technical problem. So the difference would
be from our eyes the left hand or standing on somebody is
equally technical and minor, but from a הלכה halacha side it might
be that if you're not standing on the floor of the מקדש
Mikdash you don't have the right קדושה, kedushah, you don't have your
body isn't connected to the קדושה. kedushah. But if I'm the right
person and I'm standing the right way and I'm wearing the right
clothes and I have all the right קדושה... kedushah... and I just
used the wrong limb, maybe that's more of a technical problem. Anyway,
that's all interesting to speculate on, but the גמרא Gemara generalizes it,
okay? So anyway, let's take a look.
We actually have to put it back in. Yes, you have to
put it back in, because, and that's what the גמרא Gemara will
deal with, that obviously it's not כשר, kasher, nobody's arguing that it's
כשר. kasher. The question is, have you ruined it or can you
start again? You wouldn't think the instant it spoils, just gather back
up and put it back in. So yeah, we'll get to that.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this: קמצה עלה בידו צרור Kamtza
ala beyado tzror now we get to talk also very quickly, and
much more quickly than we did when we were dealing in זבחים,
Zvachim, we get to talk with, you know, the practical nature of
the act. So קמצה עלה בידו צרור או גרגיר Kamtza ala beyado
tzror o gargar as you're doing the קמיצה, kemitza, a good old
pebble or גרגיר מלח, gargar melach, a little pebble or a little,
you know, a little piece of salt got into your hand where
the קמיצה kemitza is, או קורת של לבונה o korat shel levona
or a little piece of the incense that you bring with the
קרבן. korban. So you have a tiny little extraneous object in your
קמיצה, kemitza, פסול, pasul, it's invalid. Why? The whole thing is invalid
or just do it again? That's a good question. Okay, so well
I think we'll see that, but you know what? That's a good
point. מפני שאמרו Mipnei she’amru because they said, הקומץ היתר והחסר פסול
hakometz hayater vehachaser pasul
if you have too much in your hand or too little in
your hand, it's lacking, it's פסול. pasul. So if you have a
little rock, it's like—so your hand grasp is not full, there's a
little tiny little pebble taking the place where some more מנחה mincha
should be. Okay, ואיזהו היתר ve’eizu hayater what means too much? שקמצתו
מבורץ Shekematzto mevorat
your קומץ kometz is like bursting over. So you've got it here,
but you know a little bit is coming out high. I'm so
sorry, Patsy says you have the key? Oh, I have the master
key?
Yes. Okay, I'm sorry, I misunderstood her. All right. I don't know,
it's one of these. Okay, will you come up and get them,
or should I bring them back down? I'll come up, yeah, yeah.
Okay. So,
okay, so where are we?
מבורץ, mevorat, right, it's like bursting through.
So either it's coming out above or below or maybe it's even
through your fingers out between the fingers,
right. והחסר Vehachaser what's lacking? שקמצתו בראשי אצבעותיו Shekematzto beroshei etzbe’otav that
you did the קמיצה, kemitza, you just like used the fingertips. You
didn't like scoop it up, you know, yeah, you just like got
a little bit in your fingers. Okay. But actually that's like a
little bit of a anti-climactic. I mean, if you wanted to say
that a tiny little piece of salt makes it considered חסר, chaser,
I think I got the point. Okay. So now let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. למה לי למתני אחד מנחת חוטא ואחד
כל המנחות Lama li lemisni echad minchat chotei ve’echad kol haminchot
why do you have to say whether it's a מנחת חוטא minchat
chotei or any מנחה? mincha? ליתני כל המנחות Lisni kol haminchot all
מנחות? minchos? שקמצן זר ואונן Shekimtzan zar ve’onein
so again, you could have said because just the previous משנה mishna
we said a difference, so here we're emphasizing there's no difference. But
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. לרבי שמעון איצטריכא LeRabbi Shimon
itztericha this is needed for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, a different רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon than we've talked about before. דתניא אמר רבי שמעון
Detanya, amar Rabbi Shimon בדין הוא שתהא מנחת חוטא טעונה שמן ולבונה
bedin hu shetehei minchat chotei teu’na shemen ulevona really
a מנחה mincha for a sin, again these are like at the
end of ויקרא Vayikra like טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash or שמיעת קול
אלה, shmiat kol ala, that that should actually also require שמן ולבונה.
shemen ulevona. Why? שלא יהא חוטא נשכר Shelo yehei chotei niscar
you should not get off easy, right? You sinned, and wow, we're
telling you you can spend less money on a קרבן? korban? You
should have to bring the nice one. Now תוספות Tosafot is a
little bothered because תוספות Tosafot says that, you know, we sometimes have
fixed prices for קרבנות. korbanot. So even if we're saying you don't
need שמן ולבונה, shemen ulevona, you might have to spend the same
amount of money for a מנחה? mincha? Yeah, no,
looks like—I thought it was like the אשם asham was like two
whatever's it is. Yeah, you're right. תוספות Tosafot actually says that by—by
the חטאת. chatas. תוספות Tosafot said it by חטאת, chatas, not by
the מנחה. mincha. Okay, so let's bracket that. Okay, so שלא יהא
חוטא נשכר. Shelo yehei chotei niscar. מפני מה אינה טעונה Mipnei ma
eina teu’na why does it not need שמן ולבונה? shemen ulevona? שלא
יהא קרבנו מהודר Shelo yehei korbano mehudar so even though you're getting
a little bit of a benefit, you're not spending as much money,
but that's more important that you, you know, your קרבן korban does
not look beautiful. Your קרבן korban symbolically, right, sort of reflects the,
you know, the reality of the sense of sin. מהודר. Mehudar. ובדין
הוא שתהא חטאת חלב טעונה נסכים Uvedin hu shetehei chatat chelev teu’na
nesachim now here's the תוספות. Tosafot. A חטאת chatas of sin, the
חטאת חלב, chatat chelev, חלב chelev is the paradigm in the גמרא
Gemara for a sin that you would bring a חטאת chatas for,
something that you're חייב כרת, chayav karet, but it really means any
חטאת chatas relating
to sin as opposed to a חטאת chatas of like a נזיר
nazir or something like that. Okay. שלא יהא חוטא נשכר Shelo yehei
chotei niscar so you should actually have to bring the מנחת נסכים,
minchat nesachim, the oil, the oil and the flour and the wine
that you bring with freewill sacrifices, עולה olah or שלמים, shlamim, you
should have to bring it with a חטאת, chatas, so you shouldn't
get off easy.
מפני מה אינה טעונה Mipnei ma eina teu’na like an עולה olah
or a שלמים shlamim or a נדר נדבה, neder nedava, מפני מה
אינה טעונה mipnei ma eina teu’na why does it not? שלא יהא
קרבנו מהודר Shelo yehei korbano mehudar again, so it should not be
a very nice קרבן. korban. Now here's where תוספות Tosafot says that
there's a fixed price for חטאת, chatas, so why does it really
matter? But anyway, either way, here we see that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon actually says, you know, and again, if you remember earlier the
גמרא Gemara says that
רבי שמעון... Rabbi Shimon... using the reason for the פסוקים pesukim to
guide you and determine its halachic parameters, which we know רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon is, you're also in the enterprise of exploring what are
the reasons. Okay? It's not like the reasons are written. So, you
know, so here the גמרא Gemara already said two דפים dapim earlier
that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon will be guided by the reasons, דורשין
טעמא דקרא. dorshin ta'ama dikra. Here he's telling us there's a reason
of שלא יהא חוטא נשכר. shelo yehei chotei niscar. So maybe therefore
I would think what? Here's what I would think. סלקא דעתך אמינא
salka da'atach amina I might have thought הוה אמר רבי שמעון שלא
יהא קרבנו מהודר. hovei amar Rebbi Shimon shelo yehei korbano mehudar. I'm
sorry, not שלא יהא חוטא נשכר, shelo yehei chotei niscar, that was
his question. But his reason was שלא יהא קרבנו מהודר, shelo yehei
korbano mehudar, we don't want a beautiful קרבן korban when it's about
sin. כי קמפלגי פסולים נמי תכשר. ki kamfalei psulim nami tiskashei. Maybe
a מנחת חוטא minchat chotei we should let it be כשר kosher
even if it was improper, even if a טמא tamei person, a
non-כהן, kohen, because maybe the worse it's done the better. Now again,
that's not exactly the same as aesthetically beautiful or not aesthetically beautiful,
but nevertheless קא משמע לן. kamashmalan. So therefore it has to explicitly
say that even a מנחת חוטא minchat chotei is going to be
not good. It's a little ironic. We always assume that a מנחת
חוטא minchat chotei is easier to make invalid, but following רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon maybe we would even allow some invalidities to make it
less pleasing, less then, you know, aesthetically pleasing. So the גמרא Gemara
says, wait a minute, אי הכי התם נמי ליתני. ee hachi hatam
nami listni. So if that's true, over there in זבחים Zevachim when
we talked about the פסולים, psulim, why didn't we say אחד חטאת
חלב ואחד כל הזבחים שקבלו דמן זר ואונן? echad chatat chalav ve'echad
kol hazevachim shekiblu daman zar ve'onen? Right? Why didn't we say there,
whether it's a sin offering or whether it's any קרבן, korban, these
invalidities are problems? ולימא velayma and let's say לרבי שמעון איצטריך le'Rebbi
Shimon itzterach that we're saying that to tell you that even for
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, and even though we don't want it to
be a beautiful קרבן, korban, these are still a problem. אלמא, alma,
so אלמא, alma, כיון דתנא ליה כל ולא קתני חוץ כל משמע.
kivan detana lei kol velo katana chutz kol mashma. So over there
in זבחים Zevachim when we had a similar list and we said
כל הזבחים, kol hazevachim, so כל kol means everything and you don't
have to say explicitly חטאת. chatat. So here too, הכא נמי, hacha
nami, כיון דתנא כל ולא קתני חוץ, kivan detana kol velo katana
chutz, since it says all and it won't say except, כל משמע
kol mashma we mean everything, even the מנחת חוטא. minchat chotei. איצטריך,
itzterach, no, nevertheless you needed it here. סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach
amina I would have thought הואיל ואוקימנא לרישא דלא כרבי שמעון, ho'il
ve'ukimna lereisha delo ke'Rebbi Shimon, since we said the first משנה mishna
was not רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, right, because רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says that if you do a מנחה שלא לשמה mincha shelo lishmah
it's usually כשר kosher because you know, because what is it? קמצו,
kamtzo, not קמצו, kamtzo, קרבנו מוכיח עליו. korbano mochiach alav. There was
a big expression.
מצה מוכיח עליו, matzah mochiach alav, right, that you know the very
מציאות metzius that you're doing it from this type of a מנחה
mincha as opposed to another מנחה mincha makes it clear that your
לא לשמה lo lishmah is irrelevant. So right, the first statement of
the משנה mishna that when you do it שלא לשמה shelo lishmah
it's not good, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon disagreed with in the case
of a מנחה. mincha. So since we said the first משנה mishna
he disagreed with, סיפא נמי דלא כרבי שמעון, seifa nami delo ke'Rebbi
Shimon, I might think that this whole is all these משניות mishnayot
are not like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and that רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon would argue on our משנה mishna because of this idea of
מהודר, mehudar, קא משמע לן, kamashmalan, so it tells us otherwise. So
that was a very long discussion about what should have been an
easy answer, that the reason it says you know whether חוטא chotei
or כל מנחת חוטא kol minchat chotei is because it's juxtaposed, not
for what the גמרא Gemara said about not רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon,
but it's juxtaposed to the first משנה mishna that distinguished between a
מנחת חוטא minchat chotei and other things. Okay, be that as it
may, now we're done with our little דרש drash on the phrase
and now the גמרא Gemara what we'll stop here is going to
turn to the more central question about can you redo your act.
Okay and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and the position in the משנה
mishna that you can go back and
reverse, ואי
דתניא
אמרה. v'ee d'tanya amra.